We've danced around this topic a lot at this point,
and I love to address this.
So as a recap on the context of what we're talking about
is, at this point, we're talking about children components
trying to figure out how the heck to update the parent
component, because we've talked about the fact that, well,
we don't want to mutate props.
As we can see very clearly here, we're being yelled at.
Don't mutate props.
On the other hand, we talked about passing functions down,
as in, like, if there was a method on this component that
was called changeName, and call it this.userData.name equals,
let's say, there's an argument for newName,
and then just like that.
And so then you'd be like, OK, well, inside of user,
I'm going to pass this method, call it changeName,
and then it'll take on the reference to that method.
And then we have this changeName, which is a function.
And then it's, let's say, requiredTrue.
And then let's say we have a button here that's like, hey,
like, changeName.
That's like most people's instinctual way
in how a lot of frameworks approach this problem,
because the parent is telling it what to change,
and the child obediently does it.
The thing about this mental model, though,
is that it foregoes the fact that, actually, if we think
about how the web is designed, when
we have childdom elements, what do we have it do?
We have it bubble up events.
That's actually how the web is built natively,
if we think about it.
It's not actually the parent just telling it what to do.
It's saying, when you know that a button at a child
has happened, it bubbles up that event.
That's where we get these concepts, right?
That, oh, a click has happened.
Therefore, how does this relate to the chain of communication?
And so what we're going to talk about right now,
basically at this point, is how we can basically
emit custom events from our child
to tell the parent that something is happening.
So let's actually go ahead and just take this user card
example.
Why not?
Why wouldn't we?
So let's go ahead and just set this context up a bit.
So let me just remove this and how we would do this.
Actually, I think I might be able to leave that.
We can, for now, let's do this.
Change name.
So let's make sure everything's at least rendering correctly
on our side for the app.
OK.
So let's start with something simple,
which is that if we click a button from the child,
it will basically tell the parent that, hey,
I want to change the name.
And that when that happens, what we want it to do
is this is updated directly to Charlie.
So we won't even worry about arguments right now.
And so again, right here, just to show that this works,
if we add the click and we add change name, change now,
you'll see Ben does switch to Charlie as expected.
OK, as expected.
But this method is existing all the way up here.
So how the heck does a user card get access to that
without passing the prop down as a function?
Well, the way we do that is with this concept,
new to view 3 did not exist in View2 called emits.
And emits is the equivalent of props.
Props is saying, hey, this is what I'm expecting to send down.
Emits is our way of documenting, hey,
this is what I'm going to send up.
So if you think about it, this is actually
following the one-way data chain of unidirectional data
flow because the data comes down and then you're basically
sending a signal up to say, hey, I want something to change.
Then basically the parent knows, oh, change it,
then send that change back down.
So in that regard, it follows that traditional web model.
And so to show you what that means, we'll say emits.
So again, emit the event change name.
And so the key thing with the emits
is to think of this as custom events.
We're used to click, key up.
Those are events that are already defined for us.
This is a custom event that we're emitting.
And so what we get to do then is once we have our emits defined,
what we get to do is we get to call a global method called
emit, dollar sign emit.
And so if this is your first time using View,
you're probably wondering, what is this dollar sign here?
It's basically View's way of name scoping a global function
that is available to View specifically.
So now that this is not just something in JavaScript,
this is a View thing, we're going to emit what?
We're going to emit change name.
And this is now where the DevTools become very handy.
Inside the DevTools, there is this tab right here
called a Timeline.
And what it allows you to do is actually notice
when different events are happening.
So you notice that if I just click on the page here,
it actually does give me a timeline of snapshot
of what's happening.
It even actually has the coordinates on here I am noticing.
And so you see, it actually tells you the actual position
of what's happening.
And so when it comes to debugging,
this is pretty darn useful.
And so you notice here, though, if I click Change Name,
something happens here.
So let me scroll over.
Oop.
Oof.
I think it's losing the scroll.
OK, it's right over here.
Oop.
I think I zoomed out too much.
OK.
Refresh.
OK, there we go.
Where is my sidebar view reload components timeline?
Oh, I hit it.
Here we go.
Oh my gosh.
And I was like, where did it go?
OK, click Change Name.
And we'll see a couple of things here.
One, you see right here?
Change Name event has been omitted.
And so it's been omitted by user card.
And so you also know that it happened with a click as well.
Because you see that here, it has the mouse up,
mouse down, the click event.
And then here is where we get that Change Name event.
And you notice here, it actually tells you a little bit more
about the event info.
That is from the component user card.
The event is Change Name.
But also, we haven't gotten into this yet.
We can actually pass parameters up.
Because sometimes you're going to be customizing stuff
at the child level.
But you need to say, hey, here are some of the customizations
I'm sending up to the parent.
And this is what I'm going to send.
And so when you do this, what happens
is on your component, we get the ability to listen to what?
Listen to our custom event, which is what?
Change Name.
So this is no different than our at click, at key up.
So I'm actually going to go ahead and just do the at.
Because that's my preferred.
And then from here, what are we going to do when this is called?
We're going to run the method changeName.
OK, there we go.
I'm going to run dev.
There we go.
Yeah, I figured.
So this takes some getting used to.
Because I know that, again, this is not traditionally
how people are thinking of things.
But it's funny when we think about the primitives
were given when building with the web.
Event bubbling is a very standard way of building with things.
And more importantly, I think it allows for,
I'll call it a cleaner way of removing
that strict instructions that you're passing down
from the parent when you just pass the function.
Because now, all of a sudden, that function,
I've just seen on code bases when people do that,
it just gets hairy in terms of people,
then they start passing in the wrong function.
Because then you have to make sure
the function is doing what you want it to in the child, which
means you actually now have to check the parent
to make sure that it makes sense.
Whereas when you just emit an event,
this child component can be used in a lot of different contexts.
And then the parent can do whatever it wants with it.
And it makes sense because you're saying,
when the child component has this custom event,
I'm going to run this function, which lives in this file.
And so in that regard, it really does
help to really encapsulate that single file component
mentality while still building on web standards
and principles that we're actually
using on a day-to-day, but often overlook.
Yeah.
If you were to bubble up multiple levels,
would you have to catch it, re-emit it?
You can't just say emit, emit, emit, emit the whole way up?
You cannot.
And so that's a great question.
Because OK, so let me reiterate.
So the question here is that right now we just
have a single parent, single child, one emit, whatever.
What happens when you have a great, great, great, great,
great, great, great, great grandchild wanting
to communicate info up?
And so emits and props really are designed
for a closer relationship, like when you're closer together.
Because props actually have that same problem.
And so the pattern that's actually
the anti-pattern that's resulted from that
is called prop drilling.
And so we have app.view has this global thing,
and then you drill, drill, drill, drill,
prop, prop, prop, prop, and none of the components
use it until this one.
But then the problem with prop drilling
is that the moment you remove one in the middle,
the whole thing just falls apart immediately.
The answer to this is basically using
composables and state management in a way that,
because at that point, I would argue,
if you have data that is shared across components
at that depth, it probably makes sense
for it to be encapsulated in a module that can just
be shared across both files.
The props is really, in my mind, designed
when there's a tight coupling between the two components,
and you want it to behave a certain way.
Otherwise, what we'll see here later on
is around other flexible APIs that
allow it to do more than just these rigid instructions
between components.
Does that help to answer your question?
Is there an emit equivalent in view 2?
OK, so good question.
In regards to view 2, the dollar sign emit actually
does exist as a function.
Custom events are not new to view 3.
What is new to view 3 is the fact
that you can basically document them inside of your options.
Because the problem, and this was a misstep on,
I guess on our part, we didn't think about it,
is that when you don't have this emits property,
it seems like a small thing.
But if you start emitting multiple events,
it starts getting really hairy to track in a big component
of like, wait, what events are happening?
Where is it?
I mean, that's why we have prop definitions, too, actually.
It's to let you know, hey, what am I expecting to receive?
The emit does the opposite for us,
where what kind of events are you expecting to emit
so that people don't just randomly create their own?
And so to be clear, and just to kind of wrap that up,
if you don't like emitting directly here,
we can actually just do something like a tell parent
change name.
And this can just be a method, tell parent change name.
And we can do this dot dollar sign emit.
This would be the same exact thing.
It's up to you whether you want to call it here,
or you just want to call it inline.
Once again, I think that's more of a stylistic thing.
Because some people would be like, well,
if it's just this one event, and I'm not tracking that much,
I'm just going to inline it.
Because there's not really being reused.
On the other hand, if you have this being called a bunch of places,
you might not really want to define that everywhere.
You might want to change it in one place.